so this is my jiminy can I have 40 for
the shorts and classification so at one
time the Buddha was staying near
rajagaha in the bamboo grove then the
layman Resaca went to the nun de medina
about sat down to one side and said to
her noble lady they speak of a thing
called identity and its identities
Hollywood is Sakaya for some people will
translate that as person person
embodiment yeah no another Jyoti uh-huh
this translating is embodiment so noble
lady they speak of this thing called
identity what is this identity that the Buddha
what is this identity that the Buddha
spoke of the Sakaya the Sokka the Buddha
said that these five assumed aggregates
are Sakaya that is form feeling
perception sin Cara's determinations and
consciousness
saying the good Misaka approved and
agreed with the medina then he asked
another question
they speak of this thing called the
origin of identity what is the origin of
identity it's the craving that leads to future
it's the craving that leads to future
rebirth mixed up with relishing delight
and lust taking pleasure in various
different realms that is craving for
sensual pleasures craving for being
craving for money and the Buddha said
that that is the origin Sakaya identity
what we call the person
so what is what is what would you say
how would you explain identity what is
identity what is what what am i what is
myself
well whatever whatever you you regard
yourself to be
however vaguely so any notion of I am as
as as an individual pretty much that's
already what you take identity to be for
you so the personality so it is it is a
it is a general term it's not a specific
personality it's just the fact that
personality is their personality of a
subject so there is no sense of identity
without a sense of I'm a subject and in
other words there is there no sense of
identity without a separation between
you and the objects of your world but
all of that is not a problem that's the
result of the problem problem of craving
towards the five ideas great comes about
the rising yes that's what it says the
origin of personality so the origin
personality was not or rather is not
contained solely in the past the origin
personalities defected cravings today
once then will be there for as long as
claiming is their personality is
maintained
and craving is the is the most
immediately manifested through sense of
ownership say like when pleasant feeling
arises if you are not assuming it to be
for me mine
pertaining to me affecting me me me me
me me you wouldn't be craving for more
of it with the unpleasant feeling arises
again against me mind and I don't want
it to be and all these all these are the
kind of permutations that's why you end
up craving for it to not be could you
feel entitled to do so so to speak you
feel it's it's your right to do search
your right to defend yourself against
these feelings and it's your right to
prolong the other feelings that you want
so through that craving you maintain
your sense of ownership matures when
things present themselves as towards you
and you assume that you are because look
these things ever isn't for me so that's
that's exactly how you end up
maintaining the notion of identity of I
am such-and-such any notions of
personality that you have are the
symptoms of your underlying ownership of
things of your feelings of your
perceptions of your intentions so if you
want to undo the personality you undo
the ownership by you you can undo the
ownership as a as a matter of choice you
can decide to not own things because you
own that you will own your renunciation
of things so that some people think that
all they need to do is throw away their
possessions and they'll be free from
attachments no attachments were never in
the possessions ownership is not in the
things it's not in the aggregates so the
assumption of ownership is basically in
regard to Delegates but it's not in them
and it cannot be found anywhere else
after night as the way I described
overdone
so you don't to be trying to get rid of
the personality you want to be trying to
approve the ownership of it cuz even the
notional personalities regardless mind
because if even if you don't have you
don't take the personality personal we
don't own the personality
there is stove even the Buddha was he's
still a yeah there's a different body
word for that bubala there's the
individual underneath there it's to an
individual can have an individual
without personality but you have
personality without an individual so
individual is basically a person freed
from personality
that's why poor girl is used to describe
our hands as well and Noble disciples in
literature means an individual and
basically individual is what is left
when personality has been freed from
ownership now what is what is then left
as an individual what is there what is
absence of ownership but what is still
there is the arrogance yes but those
aggregates are not angry that pathogen
can relate to for as long as he's a
petitioner so you can't say that it's
the same aggregates the pathogen ions
and then if those are greedy to the left
for an island that's true in theory but
practically nobody can have an impartial
view on pathogen and are and spectrum
you have to be pertaining to some of it
so you are either Putrajaya or your
close to be another hunt in which case
when you speak about the five aggregates
it's going to be accurate what you refer
to but that should not then be used the
same to describe to inspire our gaze
because they're not the same that's what
it said from petitioners point of view
basically the Fargate sees for another
hunt cessation of form cessation of
consciousness says the Buddha described
it because yeah it's after cessation of
the aggregates that puto general knows
off - exactly those are the only agrees
he has aggregate still exists through
the sand
of mine let's assume that gets and never
seen Claire gets Julie no assumed that
it gets you can't see them like shoulder
to shoulder and compare them and then
sort of pick and choose or contemplate
them rightly you have to be affected by
that so by seeing that you know that
well you know you're affected by them
because you're liable to suffer your
personality this is your burden not just
the image of yourself that you have in
others but also just in general things
that can come your way things that you
don't want in the things that can go
away from you that you want to keep all
these things are our kind of
relationships of your personality and
they're all symptoms of of the
underlying problem which is kind of
overall the most general symptom of that
problem is suffering you liable to
suffer so if you're freeing yourself
from suffering you will be freeing
yourself your personality and all these
other symptoms as well because you're
freeing yourself from the underlying
cause of it
underline cause being craving so first
you need to recognize the problem the
problem is not that your person is like
personalities like this and or like that
the problem is that personality and
liability to suffering go hand in hand
it's just two aspects of the same
underlying cause two different symptoms
so once you recognize it that's the
problem you stop blaming personality to
be the problem and then try to engage in
like psychotherapy or whatever try to
rewrite your psychological patterns
around it's all management it's all just
trying to retailer the symptoms the way
you think they should be it's still a
symptom of something else something else
says the suitor says being the craving
so it's not about denying the personal
to try to get rid of it it's about
seeing it as a symptom of an underlying
cause and using it then to discern the
underlying cause because with fading
away of your ownership of your
personality as in with fading away of
those symptoms you know that the
underlying cause of the craving has been
diminished but you never be able to see
that way for as long as your practice is
about denying your personality denying
the sense of self and just arguing the
point oh there's no self the will say
there's no self look everything is
changing there is no self it's also you
know you might not like yourself because
you're angry yeah lustful these bad
habits so you want to change those
habits but you don't want to change
yourself well as I said you don't want
to you you don't want to be aiming your
efforts at changing that sense of self
because that's a symptom you want to be
aiming your efforts to the restraining
the outputs of that sense of self which
are kind of aggravating the underlying
cause that's then amplifying your sense
of self as an increase in your conceit
increasing your self-centeredness
increasing your selfishness increasing
you hate all these things and those
things are maintained and proliferated
through your actions through choices you
make and the fact that it's it's rooted
in choices means it's on you to choose
not to decide beforehand so whenever
there is a choice for wholesome or
unwholesome you choose wholesome you
don't choose unwholesome that is your
effort you don't welcome on wholesome you don't
you don't welcome on wholesome you don't
entertain it you don't engage with it
and that's how you you basically
prohibit craving to to to spread
with craving diminishing sense of self
is diminishing your conceit is
diminishing indirectly you can't say to
talk to this extent time less conceited
you can only know that in hindsight when
you stop I mean you start choosing what
you have me choosing I'll start using
wholesome its in and also I mean you've
stopped using sense restraint instead of
sensuality that's not pleasant
no of course because that is who you are
okay yeah yeah yeah you then you're
gonna have like complete identity crisis
in a sense of you lose all your
confidence that you had in the world
that you know because the world even
that you knew was the world of of
sensuality of sensual manipulations
acquiring and protections and the way
you go about it and they will have to be
undone because you'll now be drawing
from the whole domain of of sensual
being so that's the only one anxiety can
come in and out but again all those
things that are another phenomenon risen
in the same sense your personalities
phenomena reason so you use those things
as symptoms as symptoms that okay I am
actually delving in the right direction
because I'm not if I were not feeling
anxious about undoing my sense of
identity my belongings means I'm not
clearly dealing with with the underlying
cause of those things but the fact that
I am feeling anxious to fight that I'm
feeling down for means I am actually at
least going into my direction
how long have to do it I don't know
that's what the faith comes in but it's
more of a faith in finding the cure not
in faith of some magically release so
many signals in the suitors but
obviously the most obvious one is that
like the physician gives you the
medicine that's unpleasant to take but
out of the faith in physician and out of
certain discernment of your own symptoms
you get to see the symptoms at
diminishing and you keep taking the
better medicine of the painful
in their strength and so on but the
symptoms are diminishing and then
actually not just that you will not mind
the unpleasant medicine you will look
forward to it because once it heals you
you won't eat any of it it can be
painful exactly it's not always painful but when
exactly it's not always painful but when
it is you don't make a problem out of it
but sense restraint is painful only when
sense desire is there - it's painful
because of the sense desire not because
of the restraint you since say if sense
desire is not there you're not engaging
with sense objects it's not thankful
because you don't want to engage with it
so the discrepancy that was causing the
pain is gone so the question is not to
not give in to the pain and act out of
it as in trying to get rid of it by
giving in to sensuality so all these
things would be like rounding up your
your sense of your psychiatrist analogy
view that you are an independent person
independent of this experience
independent of the choices you make
you're an entity that exists on its own
you will see that that's not the case
because if you are an entity that exists
on its own why do you feel anxiety if
there are things that are doubtful or
threatening to you you would be fully
enclosed within yourself impermeable to
anything external yet you're fully
affected emotionally right from your
core but see people who are not
restrained and don't practice
mindfulness despite all the older kind
of evidence of anxiety non control
suffering they still think they are an
entity fully in charge of themselves
independent of the whole world and
everything that happens to them
you're independent not permeate the
divine world yeah yeah that's the Sakaya
sakai addicted basically the the whole
ik personality view the view that there
is this personality of me I am whatever
they might be
it's not it's obviously not even cannot
be specific I'm such as such that you
decide that upon a person sense
personality so that sense of personality
is of you that this sense of me
independent of everything else that's
why Sakaya and after after vada
it's just hand in hand it's the same
thing pretty much but once you stop
raising sense restraint to start sort of
digging up this mistaken foundation
foundations of your Sakaya you will see
that your cigar cannot be independent
from from the world your experience from
the five aggregates and you will stop
maintaining such personality view and
that's a person develop the right view
basically cuz your IP doesn't fit in the
wrong exactly
it's mutually exclusive
so this is from the bhikkhuni some Utah
ten don't know the exact number and here
we have Mara the evil one speaking to a
nun the number JIRA Samara says to her
but who is this creature formed who is
this who is the creatures maker who is
the Risen creature who is the creature
that ceases and vajira the nun says why
do you refer to the creature Mara are
you involved in your own view this is a
power of pure determinations there is
here no creature to be found just as for
an assemblage of parts there is the term
a chariot so when they are the
aggregates Convention says a creature
but it's the party term is subtle but
it's the creature and part of them
started it's closer to Pilate and Pola
then it's close then then then it's
closer to Sakaya so it's it's closer to
the individual rather than the person so
individual that's appropriate his mind
is what person is creature that's
appropriate is - it's where the question
kind of cool then who is the owner of of
this person of this you know so like the
matter they said that such as are you
what involved in the wrong view is
because the fact that he has who is the
owner of the individual means that he
puts the personality view first and then
individual second and that's exactly the
trait of the wrong view you think things
of things are yours because you are but
it's other way around you are because
you keep taking things to be yours so
that's what I mean you can you can be an
individual without being in person but
you can't be a person without being an
individual so you can have a sense of
self you can't have a sense of self
without taking things as mind but you
can be taking things as mine without
going to the extent of the sin so so
that's like the stuff that concedes
Ferrari Osaka
later on the practice so but
appropriation comes first sense of self
is the symptom of it it's the result of
it but Mara asks who is the owner of
appropriation which means he puts the
sense of self first again yeah and the
fact that she says the creature is only
a pile of determinations means pile of
choices the creature is pile of choices now
the creature is pile of choices now
wrong choices result in that creature
having a self view and thinking that its
own self is independent of his own
choices choices of ownership
thus things are mine because I am but if
the choices were right of that creature
if choices were not choices based on the
craving he will undo that view that he's
independent of his own choices
and he'll see it's just choices arising
choices ceasing determinations
manifesting determinations disappearing
so what are you talking about so the
assemblage of the parts of the chariot
is really such it's not about denying
the assemblage saying the creature
doesn't exist because it's made of parts
which is how the wrong view takes it and
certainly modern interpretations know
the creature is the name of the parts
there's no need to deny the creature and
say chariot is not real because it's
made out of components how would you
even know what those components are all
if you don't have the unifying identity
of it as a chariot same if there is no
unifying identity of an individual I the
five aggregates how can you know the
five aggregates are part of the
individual you couldn't but people hope
whereby if you sort of they hope the
you'll be able to escape the ownership
of the creature by denying its existence
through saying that it's made of parts
thus it's not real parts are real like
how can parts not be real while you're
talking about what I'm referring to is
it's based I think it's based on that
verse that the whole the questions of
the King Melinda and then the
la escena when he tried to basically
argue that there is no self because it's
made out of parts said personality Sakai
is made out of parts that's why it's not
real it is real and she says dentistry
set Convention calls its creature that
is the name of this particular
assemblage of parts which is you as a
human being and that's not a problem the
problem is you are implying ownership
maintaining ownership that then implies
the self of you as in view independent
of the assemblage of the parts but even
such mistaken view is real as a mistake
because if you keep going if you go on
denying the mistake from being there
how can you resolve it no there is a
mistake mistake is not real what is
there for you then to resolve but there
is a mistake
because there is suffering means there
is a surfer view which is a mistake so
you must acknowledge it first and that
acknowledgement is the recognition of
the wrong view which is what she has
mara based on his question implies that
clearly reveals that he puts that sense
of identity first as the owner of the
creature who is this creature form by as
if there is the entity independent of
this creature creature is second to the
entity but the right view realizes that
it isn't it's the first creature is the
basis for your end for the sense of
entity for the identity
creature is the basis for the
personality view how that's what what I
said in the previous suit is through
craving through craving in regard to
things the creature has access to
basically through craving in regard to
the family through claiming in regard to
the feelings of the creature you get to
develop the notion in you as a as an
identity is independent of this creature
I'm so much more than this body I'm so
much more than his mind how can you know
that except on the basis of your body
and mind so that's all right before we
said you keep assuming it as outside of
the creature as opposed to contained
within the creature because that's that
self do that is independence it's it's
not it's but that's well that's a view
that once in itself you yeah is infinite
in a sense you wait
eternal yeah so big that's why that's
why it's in the sense of all being
eternal and self view go hand-in-hand
you can't have you can't have a self of
you without the implicit notion of it
will last forever eternally because any
notion of lasting a cessation is on the
level of the creature and the aggregates
in the feelings but you assume yourself
to be independent of that thus you
automatically assume yourself to be
eternal so you see the notion of
eternity is within the creature is you
basically removing the basis for the
gratuitous mistake that you keep
maintaining mistake of I am independent
of the experience as a whole I am
independent of this five aggregates are
you within because you cannot occur
anywhere else except to that basis which
means you a second to it that's already
the reduction of automata antibodies
assuming that it still no sense of self
independent of the family as a whole
once you are B become unable to assume
that anymore and you will become so if
you keep rectifying your own basically
mistake of assuming it to be separate so
use you to be separate you don't deny it
that is your starting point but you now
include the assumption of separation
within the basis of the presently
enduring experience the whole since you
will rectify the mistake not put in nine
you two trying to get rid of it by by
seeing the bigger picture then includes
it bigger picture being doesn't matter
how much you conceive yourself to be
independent any notion of independence
any notion of self is within the present
enduring experience for which you had no saint
experience for which you had no saint
whatsoever and you keep practicing that
kind of contemplation that kind of
mental training and drilling off
whenever there is a sense of self
whenever there's a sense of I am it's
all gone are no real I am real but I am
within this this is not within I am and
that's like the artists our cos practice
of not I am NOT for me not like I am not
this and this is not for me how the
usual translated it's actually not is
the first I am is the second not being
the next year with you yeah so I am is
within not mine is within not self is
within not
and that's how you stop owning it and
that's how your personality will just
become an individual that's why Nara
hunt cannot be distinguished by mutagen
because all he sees his personalities he
can't see an individual through the
personality this for him individual is
personality so when our hunt speaks
talks decides tells him off shouts he'll
think oh he's an angry monk or whatever
he is a petitioner as they were casing
the suitors and it was a no he's
completely enlightened so you can't tell
it externally apart because he still has
choices preferences another one that I
want this because there was never the
problem the problem was he maintaining
the assumption of us basically an entity
separate from all of that the verse
continues to do good let's go back a bit
just as an assemblage of course there is
attempt chariot so when they are
aggregates Convention says a creature
yeah so aggregates are called the
creature the symbol yeah so it doesn't
matter if it's one part five parts
fifteen parts the name of the parts is
the creature the name of the parts of
the vehicle is chariot
well then she continues it says it is
merely suffering that comes into being
suffering it stands and well it stands
and disappears
nothing apart from suffering comes into
being nothing there other than suffering
ceases this was she's seen the mistaken
she's seen the mistaken and what's left
now it's basically just seen like when I
said just earlier on discrepancy of that
ownership means suffering so once you
once you have undone the extent of that
discrepancies and you don't assume
anymore that you are an entity dependent
of your experience as a whole
independent of anything you can see
perceive feel and intent you realize
such thing is inconceivable so your
sense of self is within those things
that are not in your control thus your
sense of self starts to fade as the
master owner of the experience which
means discrepancy begins to lessen the
discrepancy of owning the unknowable but
for as long as there trace a discrepancy
that's all the only way that's
manifested is through suffering so
whenever there is suffering minutes to
that extent there is discrepancy of
crane so a person who would say it is
many suffering it well means it's
another shock but she's not she's not
another yeah but she's not really
touched by something well yeah she might
be like warmer and it's close to not
hunt but the reason why she said that is
because that's actually as I said before
that's what's in common even to a
completely unenlightened petitioner and
somebody who is on the way to
enlightenment it is suffering and trying
to account but Regina tries to overcome
his unpleasant displeasure by going for
centrality by acting are available all that is
by acting are available all that is
rooted in you feeling the pain which
means you don't want to feel the pain so
suffering arises suffering basically
ceases and everything else you do is on
account of that literally and it's same
for iris out but now he knows that so he
doesn't go about it in the wrong way
they were made that suffering worse way
of sensuality you will distraction kale
this Bronx peach and so so he realized
that these things doesn't matter whether
it's Petrina or Betsy for a lunch if
it's all rooted in the same reason you
don't want to suffer so if that's the
goal of petitioner then you realize that
your actions are causing a massive
contradiction because it's because of
your actions you keep suffering even
more but the only reason you act is
because you don't want to suffer so
that's why meant like nobody in the top
nobody wants centrality even people full
on overview that centrality is great and
worth living for they don't want it
that's where you go to it to try and
satisfy to try to get you know yeah if
sunshine is truly pleasant there would
be no desire in regard to it you're
truly satisfied yeah
so whether it's Petrina or not all is
there is suffering in you acting out of
it so the big people with wisdom are
people who have recognized that certain
way of acting out of suffering can't
possibly bring you closer to actually
not suffer like sensory strength
mindfulness not distraction the point is
to doesn't matter where you are and even
for another hand you can say to an
extent that's what you know I don't
quite know in terms of poly what exactly
what time she used for that but even
even from from another point of view
it's not suffering anymore but there is
discomfort there is disturbance this is
too cool right you usually do proves
useful for the non-event because in
other in other sutras universities when
when person when a man becomes an errand
you'd say oh holy life has been lived
down my task so everything is better
everything that sugar abandon has been
abandoned whatever is left is basically
nuisance and discomfort that can arise
on a counter they still living both in
you know it's nothing not to care
yeah it's kind of a residue of an
arahant which is a residue of having a
living body but when this body breaks
down breaks apart there will be no more
suffering left so to speak and instead
discomfort for another hunt discomfort
of the living body discomfort of the
things arising that is the whole world
of suffering for proteges but it's
rooted in the same body exposed to
elements in these various things they
come your way so literally is nothing
it's just a pile of aggregates called
creature and discomfort manifested in
them in during ceasing and so on now
inclusion is touched by that discomfort
he grieves he suffer eleven T's and then
she took her for him when our heart is
touched by the discomfort there is no
yes but if you speak objectively yet
it's only dukkha the manifests within
this thing that we call the creature
fresh was whatever spelt it's it's it's
already a discomfort because it's a
pressure exactly yeah that's why for
another hunt he for him his attitude
ease whatever felt what Evers felt
counted suffering that's why he stops
feeling everything
see yeah she probably wasn't an island
yet because Marta was still trying to
find access to her because foreign an
event means basically mother gave up on
you the choose on the road she was on the
the choose on the road she was on the
right dog so so thinking like for
example creature is a useful deflection
thinking of yourself as a creature first
not I'm a creature cuz I am but I am
because I'm creature as the verse
describes your pile of aggregates pile
of aggregates is called creature so
there is a presence of a pile creature
is there and that none of the decision
the issue is than you developing the
ownership in regard to that whole thing
whether in regard to the pile variants
or letting out the creature
either way you develop a sense of
ownership but if you contemplate that
the necessary basis for any ownership
any sense of self anything you feel
anything you crave on account of what
you feel the necessary basis for that is
that this creature that I am is given
the pile of aggregates is given me that
would basically contain any notion of
self that you have even doesn't matter
how independent you might feel it will
be seen as a inseparable impossible to
step outside of the container of the
creature that's what the suitor says
look for the future reappearance is for
like in samsara doesn't matter in what
realm for as long as that is creating
there the that hole was taken yeah
notion of identity ownership is there
but whatever realm there is do is
there's a creature there isn't there is
always the father it's what point of
view creature is the name for the five
aggregates and as I said it's good to
like use creatures contemplation because
you say five a great seems technical
seems theoretical seems out there all
these five components if you say oh
you're sent to self-serve view well
that's a bit too close to
seen as in I am that sense sensitive but
using the term creature it's kind of
something you see that you are but it is
same time the fact that your creature
you have no say in the way that creature
manifested in how that creature and you
how long that creature will be alive so
it kind of pertains to you but it cannot
be owned in the same sense so if you
develop a context that you are a
creature you you're basically developing
a context of certain unknown ability of
your environment and your experience as
a whole of the five hundreds you deliver
in context of this passion to this tools
whatever you can experience yeah because
passion comes from that
self-centeredness from assuming that
your sense of self is independent of the
creature of the five aliens but you are
a creature first did you have seen it
any same high manifests what is its
lifespan she just any choices decisions
you make I'm gonna count that you are it
you are within it you are being being a
human being an end will be but that's
your point of views it's that's their
point of views they why do you use the
creature yeah so it doesn't matter what
environment is always a point of view in
every realm can you be can you tell to
that creature to not come anymore can
you tell to the creature to disappear
can you command it can't control it can
you be the master oh it seemed concealed
you're always the creature first any
notion of mastery ownership is within it
so that's what I mean like it's not
about denying your sense of self it's
about putting it in the right place well
except point of view
is there a separate point of view
separate a separate point of view that's
not that's independent of anything else
can it be a point of view which doesn't
do anything anymore it's inconceivable
point of view is defined by things that
are being viewed this is all two views
within the Farragut it's part of the 500
point of view you determine so that's
why it's not about getting behind the
point of view and entering
you know the supreme realm of Nibbana or
something it's about the choices you
make on account of point of view and
things that are being viewed it's all
about reaching the first point they
would kind of before which ignorant was
not there it's about not proliferating
not acting out of the unwholesome
choices not making the unwholesome
actions based on unwholesome intentions
that are fully within the point of view
what's being viewed fully within the
creature that's what the practice is
about mindfulness responsibility for
your actions and sense restraint all of
that is secondary to the point of view
you can't step outside of the point of
view and fix it as make it right because
it's not a matter of choice but you can
stop proliferating things that are
making it wrong and that's how it
becomes right indirectly
so say you can't have a sense of self
unless you're not unless you're not
already there is a creature the way you
have a reason given to yourself to
beyond basically so if you stop
maintaining the ownership of the
creature you are automatically
diminishing the self view the view of
the point of view being independent of
everything else being the first the
origin yeah the origin of things that
are being viewed so there it is coming
from me I'm within net
well I'm within whatever is present
enduring in my experience whatever
feelings present in doing whatever
intentions are presently enduring that's
I am not so you have to do this we have
no say in the rising of intentions but
then you reel it off so you do have a
sane choosing to entertain one type of
intention on account of the other
something who chooses exactly so that's
it that's a it's basically what my ass
pretty much who is choosy
yeah the fact that you asked who made
you assume that isn't person independent
of the choice wouldn't make a choice the
person is the result of the choice so
who is choosing is wrong you should say
that who is there because of choosing so
when choosing ceases to be wrong the
hoop of the choice will also diminish
and then all you have is pile of
determinations as the verse says pile of
choices but now because you haven't been
maintaining the the notion of huge who
threw around choices you get to see that
it's only choices not the who behind the
choices to say the choice chooses well
let's see that's true that that's
correct the same theory but for puja no
that's not true he chooses and he is the
result of what he chooses so he needs to
start choosing rightly first that sense
restraint sila virtue must come first
there is absolutely no Dharma without it
so who chooses is simply a wrong wrong
question that is rooted in the wrong
choices so what about free will
yeah it's the same question again free
will means choice yeah so which book
which is first may be the whole question
who chooses puts the notion of I am
first and that's some stick that's why
it's a wrong question
you can still ask it but the point is
that who chooses means there is who
first that then makes choice oh I just
need to find out who is that who but
that's good that's a wrong word it's the
choice that comes first sense of who is
secondary to it
so then we're lesbian of who chooses
becomes unintelligible because choice
comes first choice is the choice is
there that's what this is a sense of who in
that's what this is a sense of who in
regard to it because choice is owned you
stop warning choice the question of hold
subsides subsides then what stops the
person is choosing
previous choices bad choices of bad
choices are maintained for choosing
badly you stop choosing badly that's
what with a man but purifying your
action beforehand he said no you know
the young man leaves their home our
faith practices dwells not welcoming
sensuality will lives restrained
secluded he gets understand the Dhamma
he develops three-four knowledge he
frees himself because his actions have
been purified beforehand so that's what
stops you is ready choose a bad loose
you basically stop choosing badly and
choosing bad means maintenance of
choosing badly bad choices need to be
there maintained once you stopped really
badly to fade away same like like any
you know you can see that in the middle
like on a worldly level addictions to
depressing you to choose them over and
over again but then when you free
yourself from it you can't choose it
anymore because it's actually unpleasant
and now it's seen as unpleasant but
before that he was seen as Pleasant drug
addictions any other substance and form
of addiction for that matter sensuality
as an addiction say to the said it's
because you don't know it's painful
that's where you go to it like a man
with electricity burning his skin with
embers it was always painful just he
thought it was pleasant once he sees
it's painful he cannot possibly go back
to it
let's with everything that is bad will
be abandoned because everything that
it's bad requires that discrepancy of
ignorance requires its maintenance once
you stop providing that it will cease
without a reminder it cannot come back
you cannot choose badly again because
there is no more basis for bank choices
and basis for bad choices are bad
choices did you stop engaging with now
that's you remove the basis for it it is
perfect you have fear it's very fun let
go of my sense of self then I'll just do
well that's because they haven't
understood any of it you can't let go of
your sense of self as a method of choice
no if you're feeling yeah if you're
fearing that that you will let go if it
send yourself you're taking that to be a
send yourself thank God if I let go of
my responsibility you can't let go of
the responsibility you can only not the
true letting go responsibility is not a
matter of choice it's a matter of
undoing the symptoms that's it responsibility
responsibility
yeah you just stop owning it by the only
way to stop only your responsibility is
to first accept it same responsibilities
on the sense of self as we spoke before
if you keep going around saying there is
no self there is no self well how can
you undo that mistake so responsibility
is the burden that needs to be rectified
not through denying it basically going
beyond it you cannot go beyond your
responsibility for as long as you're
avoiding it so first you have to accept
responsibility that's why the the
mundane right view has to come first
there is mother
there is father there are results of my
actions as if there is the weight of my
responsibility if you go live in your
life even if you are a Buddhist
practitioner denying that very basic a
recognition of responsibility for what
you choose to do but you choose to say
how you choose to live your life what
you choose to think it's on you fully if
you're refusing to accept that
responsibility because it feels
unpleasant now wait you're refusing to
basically partake in the mundane rightly
good luck then developing the the
sacrament damar impossible
so the only way you can go beyond
responsibility is to first fully
accepting it and realizing there is no
way out
this creature is responsible for its
actions because this creature is not
free from free from its actions this
creature is not an element this creature
comes from mother father yeah there is
given there is received there is the
unknown the extents that I cannot fathom
you have made all of that as there is a
phenomena then you get to see whether
rock did where the problem is correctly
the only reason people who deny the
responsibility people will deny the
sense of self is Krishna pleasant to
admit it
that's it so again it's only suffering
that arises and suffering didn't use
whatever you do is an account of that
avoiding it
so that's all yeah the creature is a
good good time to think about as a
necessary but is full of experience as a
whole because that's the creature is the
name for the fire grains as the bill
says using the other Poliwhirl Pegula
individual which was referred to as well
as we said it's kind of it's it's sort
of less practical because people already
have up to no harm in individual he's an
individual you're an individual my
individuality you can kind of to the
language basically became appropriated
it doesn't mean the same thing anymore
I spoke elemental when the Buddha used
it to describe our hunt parrots are
workers but creature is something a
creature you are you just are to cha
creature exactly and that's exactly what
the farmer gets out they just our pile
of angry it's just a heap v Hughes
they just are you're not saying that you
cannot put a move on and they're on a
bit more you just simply have no saying
that I think you see will go for you
that you can altered or change their
order or anything like that
it's is that the favor you in a creature
that's out of your hands
so not forgetting that in the practice
of your mindfulness that you are a
creature first creature in which
creation you had no saying yet now
you're appropriating it is that the
right thing to do my sense of ownership
of this is within this creature that's
been like throwing it given to me the
way it is
so then my sense of ownership is not the
ultimate owner of this it's the result
of it so it's not the first it's the
second that's how you undo the sense of
I am over the nine but we're saying not
I am so I am NOT is first knot I knot is
the first mind is
second not like going around saying not
mind of mine setsuna videos to say is
not comma I am a second not I am so you
you stop assuming I am stepping outside
of that which is not yours
so not comes first that which is not
mine it cannot be mind that is unknowable
it cannot be mind that is unknowable
that is inconceivable and that's what
the creature is clarify what the
creature is you will stop owning it you
will cease to be a person it does not in
you